<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
      <feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
        <title>Deen Games Blog</title>
        <link href="http://deengames.com/blog" />
        <id>urn:uuid:5106a41bf528d5a51828bdccf018a5ff</id>
  	    <updated>2017-07-21T00:00:00Z</updated><entry>
      		<title>Talha's Migration, Week 3: Upgrades!</title>
          <link href="http://deengames.com/blog/2017-07-12-talhas-migration-upgrades" />
      		<id>urn:uuid:db4762a22dab2f5c4bfc72f2c754fe91</id>
      		<updated>2017-07-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
      		<summary>Talha's Migration, Week 3: Upgrades!</summary>
      		<content type="xhtml">
      			&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/JuNPgsR.gif" alt="screenshot" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, we settled the question of "should we create a separate currency, or reuse food as the currency, for in-game updates?" We decided to re-use food; relevant Reddit game-design discussion is &lt;a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/gamedesign/comments/6nhsxo/infinite_runner_additional_currency_or_food/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also made some changes to how speed works. The full list of changes this week includes:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Decision not to have a "win" state, but to continue perpetually&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Capping velocity so you can't go too fast&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;You speed up relative to how far you travel, not how much food you collect&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Food collected persists between games and sessions&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Performance optimizations (object pools for reusing objects)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Shop button takes you to the shop&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;You can buy starting-health upgrade at the shop, which persists across games and sessions&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;You can buy up to six starting health in total&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Internationalization: app is now localizable&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Localization fail for Urdu and Arabic&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While we succeeded in internationalizing our app, we only have the English localization. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two others that we can reasonably achieve (Urdu and Arabic) both use right-to-left languages. Unfortunately, HaxeFlixel doesn't yet support right-to-left-languages; the letters are disjointed (instead of connected) and left-to-right:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/gtWMQDm.png" alt="screenshot of L10N" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the results are disappointing, we at least made our app localizable. In the future, may look to the game development community to help add some localizations prior to launch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that, the plan for next week is to break out more features: what else do we need before we can ship the MVP of our game? Once we complete those, we can look into adding polish (better art, tutorial, etc.) and shipping the first version of our game in the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
      		</content>
      		<author>
      			<name>ashes999</name>
      			<email>ashes999@yahoo.com</email>
      		</author>
      	</entry>
      	<entry>
      		<title>Talha's Migration, Week 2: Core Gameplay</title>
          <link href="http://deengames.com/blog/2017-07-14-talhas-migration-mvp" />
      		<id>urn:uuid:289736cba5f1a687c347f8251855d486</id>
      		<updated>2017-07-14T00:00:00Z</updated>
      		<summary>Talha's Migration, Week 2: Core Gameplay</summary>
      		<content type="xhtml">
      			&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/iuofHjF.gif" alt="screenshot" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, we completed prototyping the major functionality for Talha's Migration. This included the core elements of the MVP version of the game:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;Speeding up after eating jellyfish (blue) and starfish (purple)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Avoiding swimming crabs (orange) and eels (yellow)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Death (three hits to die) and restarting&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game is starting to "feel" like a  real infinite runner! At this point, we need to refine the prototype and figure out what we need to add (or remove) to make it even more fun.  This includes things like:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;More predators and prey&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;In-game currency&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Permanent upgrades&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Implementing a "win" condition"&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll visit these points over the next week, and playtest to see how the game shapes up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're one of our &lt;a href="https://www.patreon.com/DeenGames"&gt;Patreon supporters&lt;/a&gt;, you should have already received a link to try the prototype in your browser.&lt;/p&gt;
      		</content>
      		<author>
      			<name>ashes999</name>
      			<email>ashes999@yahoo.com</email>
      		</author>
      	</entry>
      	<entry>
      		<title>Agile Game Development: Demos</title>
          <link href="http://deengames.com/blog/2017-07-11-agile-game-dev-demos" />
      		<id>urn:uuid:7689af8d8a5aebdbadc8f4e789407e42</id>
      		<updated>2017-07-11T00:00:00Z</updated>
      		<summary>Agile Game Development: Demos</summary>
      		<content type="xhtml">
      			&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/Zjop8Vj.jpg" alt="picture of the word: demo" /&gt;
In agile software, one of the useful processes includes showing the demo of the current sprint/iteration to customers (or a customer placeholder). How can we adopt and benefit from this practice as game developers?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This hinges on one of the key tenants of agile development: stories, or units of work, should be &lt;em&gt;user facing.&lt;/em&gt; If we can write small, user-facing units of work, and complete them, they should be demoable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the best ways to do this, while simultanously building hype for your game, is to take videos (or even GIFs) and promote them on your blog. This gives you a chance to show what you worked on, build a readership, build up hype for your game, and get the word out about what you're working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also forces you to constantly evaluate your work and make it somehow meaningful to users. When you complete something, you automatically start thinking: how can I make a short demo of it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you get into the habit of posting demos, it's easier to take this to the next step, and have a functional game that you can give your play-testers at virtually any stage of development; that's fantastic for getting real feedback on your game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also cross-promote your new blog post on social media for extra marketing &lt;em&gt;umph&lt;/em&gt;. This generates interest in your projects as they unfold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At Deen Games, we practice this. &lt;a href="http://deengames.com/blog/2017-07-07-talhas-migration-scrolling.html"&gt;Every.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://deengames.com/blog/2017-05-12-pattern-warrior-battle.html"&gt;Single.&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://deengames.com/blog/2017-05-05-pattern-warrior-nback.html"&gt;Week.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Try it, and let us know how it works out for you.&lt;/p&gt;
      		</content>
      		<author>
      			<name>ashes999</name>
      			<email>ashes999@yahoo.com</email>
      		</author>
      	</entry>
      	<entry>
      		<title>Talha's Migration, Week 1: Scrolling!</title>
          <link href="http://deengames.com/blog/2017-07-07-talhas-migration-scrolling" />
      		<id>urn:uuid:c23067dc4b2b77ba867f65717a92feda</id>
      		<updated>2017-07-07T00:00:00Z</updated>
      		<summary>Talha's Migration, Week 1: Scrolling!</summary>
      		<content type="xhtml">
      			&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/zRW6Z6m.gif" alt="screenshot" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, we made major strides on our new infinite runner project, tentatively titled "Talha's Migration." We themed the game around a loggerhead sea turtle's migration from Japan to the western coast of America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The screenshot above shows two things we implemented:&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;An infinite scrolling ground&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The player constantly moves forward.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see that when we press the left arrow, the player slows, but still moves forward; when we press right, the player accelerates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We spent a ton of time upgrading our entity-component system to handle automatic velocity and collision detection. Ultimately, the code proved to be unmanageable, and we ended up scrapping it. (We spent, literally, hours upon hours troubleshooting one collision-detection bug after another.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, we chose to employ a much simpler approach: use HaxeFlixel directly, without any intervening entity-component system. The resulting code is cleaner, clearer, and easier to write and maintain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going forward, we expect to implement (prototype) the major core features of our infinite runner ("infinite swimmer" is more like it) by next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're one of our &lt;a href="https://www.patreon.com/DeenGames"&gt;Patreon supporters&lt;/a&gt;, you can also expect a playable version of the prototype next week.&lt;/p&gt;
      		</content>
      		<author>
      			<name>ashes999</name>
      			<email>ashes999@yahoo.com</email>
      		</author>
      	</entry>
      	<entry>
      		<title>Pattern Warrior, Week 5: Battle!</title>
          <link href="http://deengames.com/blog/2017-05-12-pattern-warrior-battle" />
      		<id>urn:uuid:44c2b1bde46f42394cbb8ef0e3ca3618</id>
      		<updated>2017-05-12T00:00:00Z</updated>
      		<summary>Pattern Warrior, Week 5: Battle!</summary>
      		<content type="xhtml">
      			&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/ppchCyd.gif" alt="screenshot" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, we made several major steps forward with Pattern Warrior, which you can see captured in the GIF above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's run through them briefly.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Multiple Choice:&lt;/strong&gt; Instead of answering if you've seen a letter before, we now present players with four letters; they can pick any letter which they haven't seen that round. This provides more variety and fun, and makes the game more "game" like (as opposed to "quiz" like).&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health Potions:&lt;/strong&gt; We added health potions! You start with three, each which restores 60% (currently, 30) health. You can consume health potion at any time between rounds (prior to attacking or defending). &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Special Attack:&lt;/strong&gt; On your turn, prior to attacking, you can choose to utilize a special attack (star icon). This allows you to attack an &lt;em&gt;unlimited&lt;/em&gt; number of times (until you make a wrong choice). This will provide the player with strategic skills to use on tough battles.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also made a couple of major "invisible" changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, after much deliberation, and going in circles (should it be a game about selling sea shells? Fossils? Cooking?) we finally came full-circle and decided to theme the game as mini RPG/roguelike. You will trawl a dungeon of some number of floors, each loaded with monsters to battle, loot to find, and other things (like healing fountains).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, we decided to move beyond our initial design of mobile-only, and release this for desktop (Windows and Linux) and web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next week, given our current effort level and backlog of work, we can probably complete a lot of the roguelike elements. Hopefully, we can see an entire (albeit short) run through a floor or two of the dungeon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're one of our &lt;a href="https://www.patreon.com/DeenGames"&gt;Patreon supporters&lt;/a&gt;, you can expect a playable version of the prototype very shortly.&lt;/p&gt;
      		</content>
      		<author>
      			<name>ashes999</name>
      			<email>ashes999@yahoo.com</email>
      		</author>
      	</entry>
      	<entry>
      		<title>Pattern Warrior, Week 4: N-Back</title>
          <link href="http://deengames.com/blog/2017-05-05-pattern-warrior-nback" />
      		<id>urn:uuid:82718ccbb9c385680392f13ad27d0e1f</id>
      		<updated>2017-05-05T00:00:00Z</updated>
      		<summary>Pattern Warrior, Week 4: N-Back</summary>
      		<content type="xhtml">
      			&lt;p&gt;This week, we moved forward with Pattern Warrior. The goal is to create a small, polished web game that imrpoves players' memory as a side-effect of playing. (We walk the fine line of being "game"-like and not "memory-exercise" like.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, we finalized the two modes of gameplay we wanted to prototype: listing items from memory, and n-back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see the initial idea, regurgitating items from memory, using chunking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/aznuqs8.gif" alt="listing items screenshot" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While somewhat interesting to play, this game mode suffered from a critical flaw: &lt;a href="https://bradylab.ucsd.edu/pdfs/BradyKonkleAlvarez2009.pdf"&gt;some research&lt;/a&gt; shows that, unless linked items are related to each other, chunking itself doesn't really benefit memory. In other words, teaching players to chunk items won't improve their memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, we switched to a second prototype of a well-known memory-improvement technique called &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/N-back"&gt;n-back&lt;/a&gt;. In a nutshell, with n-back, you try to remember &lt;em&gt;N&lt;/em&gt; (or in our case, all) previously-seen items.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/7fiMJD9.gif" alt="n-back screenshot" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While more visually boring (we used letters here because it's quicker to prototype), this game mode held up much better after balance-tweaking than the memorize-these-lists gameplay.  After play-testing, it looks like this will make up the final gameplay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next week, the goal is to finalize the theme of the game (something that matches the core game loop), and add extra "gameification" features. (For these prototypes, we took the model of a simple one-on-one RPG-like battle.)&lt;/p&gt;
      		</content>
      		<author>
      			<name>ashes999</name>
      			<email>ashes999@yahoo.com</email>
      		</author>
      	</entry>
      	<entry>
      		<title>Find the Harf 2.0 Released!</title>
          <link href="http://deengames.com/blog/2017-04-28-find-the-harf-rereleased" />
      		<id>urn:uuid:c2ed6eeee44bfd1a0e16df487d91fc56</id>
      		<updated>2017-04-28T00:00:00Z</updated>
      		<summary>Find the Harf 2.0 Released!</summary>
      		<content type="xhtml">
      			&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/WRVt9Yp.png" alt="screenshot" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We finally re-released the long-awaited update of Find the Harf, our first ever Android game!  You can download it &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.deengames.findtheharf"&gt;on Google Play&lt;/a&gt; or read more about it on the &lt;a href="http://deengames.com/find-the-harf.html"&gt;Deen Games website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original version suffered from many audio problems, with a large number of users seeing audio crash entirely during play. All these problems should be resolved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, we removed the the "customize the letters shown" functionality. This was a source of endless bugs (and a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of extra work), and based on our numbers, less than 1% of our users actually use it. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope you like this new iteration!  As usual, drop us your comments here (or on Facebook) and let us know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;
      		</content>
      		<author>
      			<name>ashes999</name>
      			<email>ashes999@yahoo.com</email>
      		</author>
      	</entry>
      	<entry>
      		<title>Control Your Tongue 1.0 Released!</title>
          <link href="http://deengames.com/blog/2017-04-21-control-your-tongue-released" />
      		<id>urn:uuid:5549c2f304578c81185fbee9fada2fb0</id>
      		<updated>2017-04-21T00:00:00Z</updated>
      		<summary>Control Your Tongue 1.0 Released!</summary>
      		<content type="xhtml">
      			&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="http://i.imgur.com/EQRchUv.png" alt="screenshot" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're excited to announce our very first Android app, Control Your Tongue! This app helps kids aged 5-9 practice makhraj (pronounciation) of the Arabic letters, while reciting words used throughout the Qur'an.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can download it &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.deengames.controlyourtongue"&gt;on Google Play&lt;/a&gt; or read about it &lt;a href="http://deengames.com/control-your-tongue.html"&gt;on our website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can compare your voice to a pre-recorded version to see how close you can get to the intended recitation; and you can choose whichever letters and makharij to go through, at your own pace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We created this game over a month, as a collaborative effort with a new developer. This early version ships with only one makharij (jawf / oral-cavity). InshaAllah we plan to add more over the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We hope you enjoy it and benefit from it!  As usual, drop us your comments here (or on Facebook) and let us know what you think.&lt;/p&gt;
      		</content>
      		<author>
      			<name>ashes999</name>
      			<email>ashes999@yahoo.com</email>
      		</author>
      	</entry>
      	</feed>